<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<sect1 id="release-7-8-4">
  <title>Release notes for version 7.8.4</title>

  <para>
    The 7.8.4 release is a bugfix release. The major bugfixes relative
    to 7.8.3 are listed below.
  </para>

  <sect2>
    <title>GHC</title>

    <itemizedlist>
       <listitem>
          <para>
	    A critical bug in the LLVM backend which would cause the
	    compiler to generate incorrect code has been fixed (issue
	    #9439).
          </para>
       </listitem>
       <listitem>
          <para>
	    Several bugs in the code generator have been fixed for
	    unregisterised platforms, such as 64bit PowerPC (issue
	    #8819 and #8849).
          </para>
       </listitem>
       <listitem>
          <para>
	    A bug that could cause GHC's constructor specialization
	    pass (enabled by default at <literal>-O2</literal>, or via
	    <literal>-fspec-constr</literal>) to loop forever and
	    consume large amounts of memory has been fixed (issue
	    #8960).
          </para>
       </listitem>
       <listitem>
          <para>
	    A bug that would cause GHC to fail when attempting to
	    determine GCC's version information in non-english locales
	    has been fixed (issue #8825).
          </para>
       </listitem>
       <listitem>
          <para>
	    A minor bug that allowed GHC to seemingly import (but not
	    use) private data constructors has been fixed (issue
	    #9006).
          </para>
       </listitem>
       <listitem>
          <para>
	    A bug in the register allocator which would cause GHC to
	    crash during compilation has been fixed (issue #9303).
          </para>
       </listitem>
       <listitem>
          <para>
	    A bug that caused the compiler to panic on some input C--
	    code has been fixed (issue #9329).
          </para>
       </listitem>
       <listitem>
          <para>
	    A few various minor deadlocks in the runtime system when
	    using <literal>forkProcess</literal> have been fixed.
          </para>
       </listitem>
       <listitem>
          <para>
	    A bug which made blocked STM transactions
	    non-interruptible has been fixed (issue #9379).
          </para>
       </listitem>
       <listitem>
          <para>
	    A bug in the compiler which broke pattern synonym imports
	    across modules in Haddock has been fixed (issue #9417).
          </para>
       </listitem>
       <listitem>
          <para>
	    A minor bug in the code generator in which the
	    <literal>popCnt16#</literal> did not zero-extend its
	    result has been fixed (issue #9435).
          </para>
       </listitem>
       <listitem>
          <para>
	    A minor bug in the compiler which made error messages emit
	    necessary parenthesis has been fixed (issue #9658).
          </para>
       </listitem>
       <listitem>
          <para>
	    A bug which caused the compiler to panic on pattern
	    synonyms inside a class declaration has been fixed (issue
	    #9705).
          </para>
       </listitem>
       <listitem>
          <para>
	    A bug in the typechecker revolving around un-saturated
	    type family applications has been fixed (issue #9433).
          </para>
       </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </sect2>
</sect1>
