<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!-- FFI docs as a chapter -->

<chapter id="ffi">
 <title>
Foreign function interface (FFI)
 </title>

  <para>GHC (mostly) conforms to the Haskell 98 Foreign Function Interface
  Addendum 1.0, whose definition is available from <ulink url="http://haskell.org/"><literal>http://haskell.org/</literal></ulink>.</para>

  <para>To enable FFI support in GHC, give the <option>-fffi</option><indexterm><primary><option>-fffi</option></primary>
    </indexterm> flag, or
the <option>-fglasgow-exts</option><indexterm><primary><option>-fglasgow-exts</option></primary>
    </indexterm> flag which implies <option>-fffi</option>
.</para>

  <para>GHC implements a number of GHC-specific extensions to the FFI
    Addendum.  These extensions are described in <xref linkend="ffi-ghcexts" />, but please note that programs using
    these features are not portable.  Hence, these features should be
    avoided where possible.</para>

  <para>The FFI libraries are documented in the accompanying library
  documentation; see for example the
    <ulink url="../libraries/base/Control-Concurrent.html"><literal>Foreign</literal></ulink> module.</para>

  <sect1 id="ffi-ghcexts">
    <title>GHC extensions to the FFI Addendum</title>

    <para>The FFI features that are described in this section are specific to
    GHC.  Your code will not be portable to other compilers if you use them.</para>

    <sect2>
      <title>Unboxed types</title>

      <para>The following unboxed types may be used as basic foreign types
      (see FFI Addendum, Section 3.2): <literal>Int#</literal>,
      <literal>Word#</literal>, <literal>Char#</literal>,
      <literal>Float#</literal>, <literal>Double#</literal>,
      <literal>Addr#</literal>, <literal>StablePtr# a</literal>,
      <literal>MutableByteArray#</literal>, <literal>ForeignObj#</literal>,
      and <literal>ByteArray#</literal>.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="ffi-newtype-io">
      <title>Newtype wrapping of the IO monad</title>
      <para>The FFI spec requires the IO monad to appear in various  places,
      but it can sometimes be convenient to wrap the IO monad in a
      <literal>newtype</literal>, thus:
<programlisting>
  newtype MyIO a = MIO (IO a)
</programlisting>
     (A reason for doing so might be to prevent the programmer from
	calling arbitrary IO procedures in some part of the program.)
</para>
<para>The Haskell FFI already specifies that arguments and results of
foreign imports and exports will be automatically unwrapped if they are 
newtypes (Section 3.2 of the FFI addendum).  GHC extends the FFI by automatically unwrapping any newtypes that
wrap the IO monad itself.
More precisely, wherever the FFI specification requires an IO type, GHC will
accept any newtype-wrapping of an IO type.  For example, these declarations are
OK:
<programlisting>
   foreign import foo :: Int -> MyIO Int
   foreign import "dynamic" baz :: (Int -> MyIO Int) -> CInt -> MyIO Int
</programlisting>
</para>
      </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="ffi-ghc">
    <title>Using the FFI with GHC</title>

    <para>The following sections also give some hints and tips on the
    use of the foreign function interface in GHC.</para>

    <sect2 id="foreign-export-ghc">
      <title>Using <literal>foreign export</literal> and <literal>foreign import ccall "wrapper"</literal> with GHC</title>

      <indexterm><primary><literal>foreign export
      </literal></primary><secondary>with GHC</secondary>
      </indexterm>

      <para>When GHC compiles a module (say <filename>M.hs</filename>)
      which uses <literal>foreign export</literal> or 
      <literal>foreign import "wrapper"</literal>, it generates two
      additional files, <filename>M_stub.c</filename> and
      <filename>M_stub.h</filename>.  GHC will automatically compile
      <filename>M_stub.c</filename> to generate
      <filename>M_stub.o</filename> at the same time.</para>

      <para>For a plain <literal>foreign export</literal>, the file
      <filename>M_stub.h</filename> contains a C prototype for the
      foreign exported function, and <filename>M_stub.c</filename>
      contains its definition.  For example, if we compile the
      following module:</para>

<programlisting>
module Foo where

foreign export ccall foo :: Int -> IO Int

foo :: Int -> IO Int
foo n = return (length (f n))

f :: Int -> [Int]
f 0 = []
f n = n:(f (n-1))</programlisting>

      <para>Then <filename>Foo_stub.h</filename> will contain
      something like this:</para>

<programlisting>
#include "HsFFI.h"
extern HsInt foo(HsInt a0);</programlisting>

      <para>and <filename>Foo_stub.c</filename> contains the
      compiler-generated definition of <literal>foo()</literal>.  To
      invoke <literal>foo()</literal> from C, just <literal>#include
      "Foo_stub.h"</literal> and call <literal>foo()</literal>.</para>

      <para>The <filename>foo_stub.c</filename> and
	<filename>foo_stub.h</filename> files can be redirected using the
	<option>-stubdir</option> option; see <xref linkend="options-output"
	  />.</para>

      <para>When linking the program, remember to include
        <filename>M_stub.o</filename> in the final link command line, or
        you'll get link errors for the missing function(s) (this isn't
        necessary when building your program with <literal>ghc
        &ndash;&ndash;make</literal>, as GHC will automatically link in the
        correct bits).</para>

      <sect3 id="using-own-main"> 
	<title>Using your own <literal>main()</literal></title>

	<para>Normally, GHC's runtime system provides a
	<literal>main()</literal>, which arranges to invoke
	<literal>Main.main</literal> in the Haskell program.  However,
	you might want to link some Haskell code into a program which
	has a main function written in another language, say C.  In
	order to do this, you have to initialize the Haskell runtime
	system explicitly.</para>

	<para>Let's take the example from above, and invoke it from a
	standalone C program.  Here's the C code:</para>

<programlisting>
#include &lt;stdio.h&gt;
#include "HsFFI.h"

#ifdef __GLASGOW_HASKELL__
#include "foo_stub.h"
#endif

#ifdef __GLASGOW_HASKELL__
extern void __stginit_Foo ( void );
#endif

int main(int argc, char *argv[])
{
  int i;

  hs_init(&amp;argc, &amp;argv);
#ifdef __GLASGOW_HASKELL__
  hs_add_root(__stginit_Foo);
#endif

  for (i = 0; i &lt; 5; i++) {
    printf("%d\n", foo(2500));
  }

  hs_exit();
  return 0;
}</programlisting>

	<para>We've surrounded the GHC-specific bits with
	<literal>#ifdef __GLASGOW_HASKELL__</literal>; the rest of the
	code should be portable across Haskell implementations that
	support the FFI standard.</para>

	<para>The call to <literal>hs_init()</literal>
	initializes GHC's runtime system.  Do NOT try to invoke any
	Haskell functions before calling
	<literal>hs_init()</literal>: bad things will
	undoubtedly happen.</para>

	<para>We pass references to <literal>argc</literal> and
	<literal>argv</literal> to <literal>hs_init()</literal>
	so that it can separate out any arguments for the RTS
	(i.e. those arguments between
	<literal>+RTS...-RTS</literal>).</para>

	<para>Next, we call
	<function>hs_add_root</function><indexterm><primary><function>hs_add_root</function></primary>
	</indexterm>, a GHC-specific interface which is required to
	initialise the Haskell modules in the program.  The argument
	to <function>hs_add_root</function> should be the name of the
	initialization function for the "root" module in your program
	- in other words, the module which directly or indirectly
	imports all the other Haskell modules in the program.  In a
	standalone Haskell program the root module is normally
	<literal>Main</literal>, but when you are using Haskell code
	from a library it may not be.  If your program has multiple
	root modules, then you can call
	<function>hs_add_root</function> multiple times, one for each
	root.  The name of the initialization function for module
	<replaceable>M</replaceable> is
	<literal>__stginit_<replaceable>M</replaceable></literal>, and
	it may be declared as an external function symbol as in the
	code above.  Note that the symbol name should be transformed
	according to the Z-encoding:</para>

      <informaltable>
	<tgroup cols="2" align="left" colsep="1" rowsep="1">
	  <thead>
	    <row>
	      <entry>Character</entry>
	      <entry>Replacement</entry>
	    </row>
	  </thead>
	  <tbody>
	    <row>
	      <entry><literal>.</literal></entry>
	      <entry><literal>zd</literal></entry>
	    </row>
	    <row>
	      <entry><literal>_</literal></entry>
	      <entry><literal>zu</literal></entry>
	    </row>
	    <row>
	      <entry><literal>`</literal></entry>
	      <entry><literal>zq</literal></entry>
	    </row>
	    <row>
	      <entry><literal>Z</literal></entry>
	      <entry><literal>ZZ</literal></entry>
	    </row>
	    <row>
	      <entry><literal>z</literal></entry>
	      <entry><literal>zz</literal></entry>
	    </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </informaltable>

	<para>After we've finished invoking our Haskell functions, we
	can call <literal>hs_exit()</literal>, which terminates the
	RTS.</para>

	<para>There can be multiple calls to
	<literal>hs_init()</literal>, but each one should be matched
	by one (and only one) call to
	<literal>hs_exit()</literal><footnote><para>The outermost
	<literal>hs_exit()</literal> will actually de-initialise the
	system.  NOTE that currently GHC's runtime cannot reliably
	re-initialise after this has happened.</para>
	</footnote>.</para>

	<para>NOTE: when linking the final program, it is normally
	easiest to do the link using GHC, although this isn't
	essential.  If you do use GHC, then don't forget the flag
	<option>-no-hs-main</option><indexterm><primary><option>-no-hs-main</option></primary>
	  </indexterm>, otherwise GHC will try to link
	to the <literal>Main</literal> Haskell module.</para>
      </sect3>

      <sect3 id="ffi-library">
        <title>Making a Haskell library that can be called from foreign
          code</title>

        <para>The scenario here is much like in <xref linkend="using-own-main"
            />, except that the aim is not to link a complete program, but to
          make a library from Haskell code that can be deployed in the same
          way that you would deploy a library of C code.</para>

        <para>The main requirement here is that the runtime needs to be
          initialized before any Haskell code can be called, so your library
          should provide initialisation and deinitialisation entry points,
          implemented in C or C++.  For example:</para>

<programlisting>
 HsBool mylib_init(void){
   int argc = ...
   char *argv[] = ...

   // Initialize Haskell runtime
   hs_init(&amp;argc, &amp;argv);

   // Tell Haskell about all root modules
   hs_add_root(__stginit_Foo);

   // do any other initialization here and
   // return false if there was a problem
   return HS_BOOL_TRUE;
 }

 void mylib_end(void){
   hs_exit();
 }
</programlisting>

        <para>The initialisation routine, <literal>mylib_init</literal>, calls
          <literal>hs_init()</literal> and <literal>hs_add_root()</literal> as
          normal to initialise the Haskell runtime, and the corresponding
          deinitialisation function <literal>mylib_end()</literal> calls
          <literal>hs_exit()</literal> to shut down the runtime.</para>
      </sect3>

      <sect3 id="hs-exit">
        <title>On the use of <literal>hs_exit()</literal></title>

        <para><literal>hs_exit()</literal> normally causes the termination of
          any running Haskell threads in the system, and when
          <literal>hs_exit()</literal> returns, there will be no more Haskell
          threads running.  The runtime will then shut down the system in an
          orderly way, generating profiling
          output and statistics if necessary, and freeing all the memory it
          owns.</para>

        <para>It isn't always possible to terminate a Haskell thread forcibly:
          for example, the thread might be currently executing a foreign call,
          and we have no way to force the foreign call to complete.  What's
          more, the runtime must
          assume that in the worst case the Haskell code and runtime are about
          to be removed from memory (e.g. if this is a <link linkend="win32-dlls">Windows DLL</link>,
          <literal>hs_exit()</literal> is normally called before unloading the
          DLL).  So <literal>hs_exit()</literal> <emphasis>must</emphasis> wait
          until all outstanding foreign calls return before it can return
          itself.</para>

        <para>The upshot of this is that if you have Haskell threads that are
          blocked in foreign calls, then <literal>hs_exit()</literal> may hang
          (or possibly busy-wait) until the calls return.  Therefore it's a
          good idea to make sure you don't have any such threads in the system
          when calling <literal>hs_exit()</literal>.  This includes any threads
          doing I/O, because I/O may (or may not, depending on the
          type of I/O and the platform) be implemented using blocking foreign
          calls.</para>

        <para>The GHC runtime treats program exit as a special case, to avoid
          the need to wait for blocked threads when a standalone
          executable exits.  Since the program and all its threads are about to
          terminate at the same time that the code is removed from memory, it
          isn't necessary to ensure that the threads have exited first.
          (Unofficially, if you want to use this fast and loose version of
          <literal>hs_exit()</literal>, then call
          <literal>shutdownHaskellAndExit()</literal> instead).</para> 
      </sect3>
    </sect2>
    
    <sect2 id="glasgow-foreign-headers">
      <title>Using function headers</title>

      <indexterm><primary>C calls, function headers</primary></indexterm>

      <para>When generating C (using the <option>-fvia-C</option>
      flag), one can assist the C compiler in detecting type
      errors by using the <option>-&num;include</option> directive
      (<xref linkend="options-C-compiler"/>) to provide
      <filename>.h</filename> files containing function
      headers.</para>

      <para>For example,</para>

<programlisting>
#include "HsFFI.h"

void         initialiseEFS (HsInt size);
HsInt        terminateEFS (void);
HsForeignObj emptyEFS(void);
HsForeignObj updateEFS (HsForeignObj a, HsInt i, HsInt x);
HsInt        lookupEFS (HsForeignObj a, HsInt i);
</programlisting>

      <para>The types <literal>HsInt</literal>,
      <literal>HsForeignObj</literal> etc. are described in the H98 FFI
      Addendum.</para>

      <para>Note that this approach is only
      <emphasis>essential</emphasis> for returning
      <literal>float</literal>s (or if <literal>sizeof(int) !=
      sizeof(int *)</literal> on your architecture) but is a Good
      Thing for anyone who cares about writing solid code.  You're
      crazy not to do it.</para>

<para>
What if you are importing a module from another package, and
a cross-module inlining exposes a foreign call that needs a supporting
<option>-&num;include</option>?  If the imported module is from the same package as
the module being compiled, you should supply all the <option>-&num;include</option>
that you supplied when compiling the imported module.  If the imported module comes
from another package, you won't necessarily know what the appropriate 
<option>-&num;include</option> options are; but they should be in the package 
configuration, which GHC knows about.  So if you are building a package using
        Cabal, remember to put all those include files in the package
        description (see the <literal>includes</literal> field in the Cabal
        documentation).</para>

<para>
It is also possible, according the FFI specification, to put the 
<option>-&num;include</option> option in the foreign import 
declaration itself:
<programlisting>
  foreign import "foo.h f" f :: Int -> IO Int
</programlisting>
When compiling this module, GHC will generate a C file that includes
the specified <option>-&num;include</option>.  However, GHC
<emphasis>disables</emphasis> cross-module inlining for such foreign
calls, because it doesn't transport the <option>-&num;include</option>
information across module boundaries.  (There is no fundamental reason for this;
it was just tiresome to implement.  The wrapper, which unboxes the arguments
etc, is still inlined across modules.)  So if you want the foreign call itself
to be inlined across modules, use the command-line and package-configuration
<option>-&num;include</option> mechanism.
</para>

      <sect3 id="finding-header-files">
	<title>Finding Header files</title>

	<para>Header files named by the <option>-&num;include</option>
	option or in a <literal>foreign import</literal> declaration
	are searched for using the C compiler's usual search path.
	You can add directories to this search path using the
	<option>-I</option> option (see <xref
	linkend="c-pre-processor"/>).</para>

	<para>Note: header files are ignored unless compiling via C.
	If you had been compiling your code using the native code
	generator (the default) and suddenly switch to compiling via
	C, then you can get unexpected errors about missing include
	files.  Compiling via C is enabled automatically when certain
	options are given (eg. <option>-O</option> and
	<option>-prof</option> both enable
	<option>-fvia-C</option>).</para>
      </sect3>

    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>Memory Allocation</title>

      <para>The FFI libraries provide several ways to allocate memory
      for use with the FFI, and it isn't always clear which way is the
      best.  This decision may be affected by how efficient a
      particular kind of allocation is on a given compiler/platform,
      so this section aims to shed some light on how the different
      kinds of allocation perform with GHC.</para>

      <variablelist>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term><literal>alloca</literal> and friends</term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>Useful for short-term allocation when the allocation
	    is intended to scope over a given <literal>IO</literal>
	    computation.  This kind of allocation is commonly used
	    when marshalling data to and from FFI functions.</para>

	    <para>In GHC, <literal>alloca</literal> is implemented
	    using <literal>MutableByteArray#</literal>, so allocation
	    and deallocation are fast: much faster than C's
	    <literal>malloc/free</literal>, but not quite as fast as
	    stack allocation in C.  Use <literal>alloca</literal>
	    whenever you can.</para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>

	<varlistentry>
	  <term><literal>mallocForeignPtr</literal></term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>Useful for longer-term allocation which requires
	    garbage collection.  If you intend to store the pointer to
	    the memory in a foreign data structure, then
	    <literal>mallocForeignPtr</literal> is
	    <emphasis>not</emphasis> a good choice, however.</para>

	    <para>In GHC, <literal>mallocForeignPtr</literal> is also
	    implemented using <literal>MutableByteArray#</literal>.
	    Although the memory is pointed to by a
	    <literal>ForeignPtr</literal>, there are no actual
	    finalizers involved (unless you add one with
	    <literal>addForeignPtrFinalizer</literal>), and the
	    deallocation is done using GC, so
	    <literal>mallocForeignPtr</literal> is normally very
	    cheap.</para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>

	<varlistentry>
	  <term><literal>malloc/free</literal></term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>If all else fails, then you need to resort to
	    <literal>Foreign.malloc</literal> and
	    <literal>Foreign.free</literal>.  These are just wrappers
	    around the C functions of the same name, and their
	    efficiency will depend ultimately on the implementations
	    of these functions in your platform's C library.  We
	    usually find <literal>malloc</literal> and
	    <literal>free</literal> to be significantly slower than
	    the other forms of allocation above.</para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>

	<varlistentry>
	  <term><literal>Foreign.Marshal.Pool</literal></term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>Pools are currently implemented using
	    <literal>malloc/free</literal>, so while they might be a
	    more convenient way to structure your memory allocation
	    than using one of the other forms of allocation, they
	    won't be any more efficient.  We do plan to provide an
	    improved-performance implementation of Pools in the
	    future, however.</para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>
</chapter>

<!-- Emacs stuff:
     ;;; Local Variables: ***
     ;;; mode: xml ***
     ;;; sgml-parent-document: ("users_guide.xml" "book" "chapter") ***
     ;;; End: ***
 -->
